Inventory to the Records of the Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project (ERACAP) (1970-1985)
Sophia Smith Collection
Frances Fitzgerald interviews Beth McAllister, specifically focusing on Pat Blackstone and her involvement in the League of Women Voters and ERA education as it relates to grassroots education and organizing in Catawba County, North Carolina. Other topics include abortion, economic issues, daycare and education, social programs, juvenile justice, welfare, the fair employment bill, "equal pay for equal work," and property laws.
#85, "Allsbrook after Senate, NC State legislature, 1979"
Senator Allsbrook discusses the North Carolina Constitutional Amendments Committee's actions concerning the ERA. The press asks Allsbrook questions about the committee process and procedure, his personal views on the ERA, and his motivations for bringing the bill to a vote before the General Assembly. An unidentified woman talks about water conservation, reservoirs, drought, and the history of water supplies in California.
#86, "Anti-ERA rally, 14 year old speech; 2 interviews with anti ERA folk, n.d."
An anti-ERA rally takes place outside of the North Carolina Legislature. Fourteen-year old Lisa Kazmirczak from Carroll Junior High gives a speech explaining her reasons for being anti-ERA and encouraging junior high and high school female students to attend anti-ERA rallies. She then answers questions from the press as to how and why the girls were organized, why they mobilized girls and not boys, and the involvement of the Girl Scouts and the Fayetteville Church adult group. Next, a group of anti-ERA women discuss their reasons for opposing the bill. Other footage includes interviews with various ERA opponents, including anti-ERA protestors outside of the NC Legislature. The DVD concludes with a brief interview with a supporter of the ERA.
#87, "Sen. Wichard; Sen. Cecil Hill; Senate floor, n.d."
The North Carolina Constitutional Committee addresses Senator Robert Davis' absence from a previous meeting and the subsequent process of a re-vote concerning the ERA bill. The Judiciary Committee is shown meeting to discuss a substitute motion proposed by Senator Allsbrook to discuss the ERA at another meeting next week. The University of North Carolina television station reports on the Senate Committee vote on the ERA, Senator Walter Cockerham's ERA survey, and shows other footage of the legislature's actions concerning the ERA.
#88, "ERA Rally Washington, D.C. June 30, 1981"
A pro-ERA rally in Washington, D.C. includes pro-ERA songs, and speeches by a NOW representative and Alan Alda. Others demonstrating include Beth McAllister and Sonya Quinn.
#89, "ERA Rally Washington, D.C., Roll 2, June 30, 1981"
Continuing footage of the pro-ERA rally in Washington, D.C. A NOW representative finishes her speech. Arlene Alda (wife of Alan Alda) gives a speech, and various labor union representatives give speeches, including the AFL-CIO and the Communication Workers of America. A member of the Democratic National Party also voices his support for the ERA and questions the Republicans' opposition to the bill.
#90, "ERA Rally Washington, D.C., Roll 3, June 30, 1981"
Continuing footage of the pro-ERA rally in Washington, D.C. Footage includes more speeches in support of the ERA and the performance of a pro-ERA song. Lynn Cutler calls for the first national vigil in favor of the ERA and discusses the ERA in terms of religion and the Bible. The president of the National Federation of Priests' Councils gives a speech in which he says that the priests voted by a 96% majority to support the ERA. Beth McAllister and her friend Jackie discuss the history of the ERA in the North Carolina legislature and the future of the bill.
#91, "ERA Rally Washington, D.C., tape 4, June 30, 1981"
Continuing footage of Beth McAllister, Miriam Dorsey, and Jackie at the pro-ERA rally in Washington, D.C. They discuss the attitudes of anti-ERA legislators, the inclusion of minority women in the women's rights movement nationally and in North Carolina, their individual roles within the movement, the Reagan administration, "the feminization of poverty," the Family Protection Act, etc.
#92, "ERA Rally Washington, D.C., Roll 5, June 30, 1981"
Continuing footage of Beth McAllister, Miriam Dorsey, and Jackie at the pro-ERA rally in Washington, D.C. They discuss the Women's Political Caucus, conservative politician Richard Viguerie, Virginia's fight for the ERA, the ERA Candlelight Vigil, etc. Footage then shifts to CBS news coverage of the Reagan-Carter election.
#93, "ERA Rally Washington, D.C., Roll 7, June 30, 1981"
This footage is misidentified and is not the ERA rally. A woman is interviewed about the various reasons why people vote (or do not vote), such as family voting traditions, the difficulty of registration mobility, and frustration over the state of national affairs. She also discusses the Reagan-Carter election rather in-depth, including the demographics of each candidate's supporters, the role of the media, each candidate's major ideologies, etc.
#94, "ERA Press conference, tape 1 of 2, June 17/18, 1981"
At a press conference in the North Carolina Legislature, Beth McAllister and Lynn Cutler give pro-ERA speeches. Topics include the actions and successes of the various North Carolina pro-ERA groups, the national Democratic Party's views on the ERA, Governor James Hunt's support for the ERA, and the need for the ERA's ratification.
#95, "ERA Press conference, tape 2 of 2, June 17/18, 1981"
Continuing footage of the North Carolina Legislature press conference. Beth McAllister and Lynn Cutler answer questions from the press. Topics include the 1981 legislative session, the goal for the ratification of the ERA in North Carolina by 1982, and Governor Hunt's support for the ERA. Filming then shifts to a North Carolinian legislative committee's discussion of an energy bill, proposed by Governor Hunt.
#96, "Kessee on ERA, 1981"
Footage shows North Carolina Republican Representative Margaret P. Kessee-Forrester discussing the ERA at a press conference. Topics include redistricting, the possibility of ERA ratification, and the history of the women's rights movement. Filming then shifts to a press conference with Governor James Hunt. Topics include the state's budget and the status of various bills. Beth McAllister's speech at the press conference, in which she introduces Lynn Cutler is also shown (similar to #95 footage).
#97, "ERA Legislative proceedings, Raleigh, NC, 1979"
Senate legislative proceedings regarding the ERA. Filming then shifts to an interview with Representative Jack Stevens. He discusses the past, present, and future of the ERA. Senate legislative proceedings regarding the ERA continue.
#98, "ERA Constitutional Amendment Committee, February 15, 1979"
Senator Davis explains a bill pertaining to a simple word change in the NC Constitution. Senator Alexander proposes to kill the ERA bill in committee ("give it an unfavorable report"), and Senator Rachel Gray challenges him, thus sparking a discussion and debate among the various senators.
#99, "Family Protection Act PC#1, June 17, 1981"
Republican Senator Roger Jepsen from Iowa and Republican Senator Paul Laxalt from Nevada discuss their sponsorship of and commitment to the Family Protection Act at a banquet reception in Washington, D.C. Representative Smith also gives a speech in support of the Family Protection Act.
#100, "Press Conference Family Protection Act, tape 3, June 17, 1981"
Senator Jepsen, Senator Laxalt, and Representative Smith answer questions about the Family Protection Act. Topics include how the bill relates to the ERA, the moral decay of the family, the effects of radical feminism on the country, secular humanism, and the decline of religious education in the schools. Representative Smith and his wife answer more questions about the bill (especially in reference to feminism, sex education, and the ERA).
#101, "Anti pornography/obscenity, Raleigh NC, tape 1, June 5, 1981"
A subcommittee of the North Carolina Senate discusses a proposed anti-pornography/obscenity bill (Senate Bill 295). The senators discuss, debate, and read various statements for and against the proposed bill.
#102, "Anti pornography/obscenity, Raleigh NC, tape 2, June 5, 1981"
A subcommittee of the North Carolina House of Representatives discusses a proposed anti-pornography/obscenity bill (Senate Bill 295). A lawyer for the Motion Picture Association of America, a representative of the public libraries of North Carolina association, a lawyer for a videotape company, a lawyer for a periodical association, a representative for the North Carolina Civil Liberties Union, and Senator Jordan, on behalf of the association of theaters of North Carolina, read statements in opposition to the bill. Filming then shifts to a committee meeting on a referendum regarding a bill about the legal age for purchasing/drinking alcohol. The DVD concludes with footage of the North Carolina House of Representatives.
#103, "NOW march, 1978"
Footage shows a 1978 pro-ERA rally, including ERA songs, speeches, and various groups of women discussing their views and experiences concerning the ERA and the women's rights movement.
#104, "NOW march, tape 2, 1978"
*Video stops at 8:20-minute mark; country folk music plays for the remainder of the time.
An ERA supporter from Virginia, Laurabelle Yoder, meets with Democratic U.S. Representative David E. Satterfield, III (D-Virginia). They discuss Senator Sam Ervin, misconceptions about the ERA, and Satterfield's views on the potential seven-year extension. After their meeting, Yoder cries in frustration and explains to another ERA supporter how the meeting went.
#105, "Excerpt, Abortion show, 1979"
Excerpts from a T.V. show on abortion, focusing on the religious aspects; interviews with various religious leaders.
#106, "Phyllis Schlafly; anti ERA group, October 4, n.d."
A conversation with a group of anti-ERA supporters from Texas in the U.S. Senate in Washington, D.C. Phyllis Schlafly Is interviewed about her anti-ERA views, her belief that the media is biased in favor of pro-ERA advocates, her personal reasons for becoming active in the anti-ERA movement, the demographics of the anti-ERA movement, her home state of Illinois, the monetary contributions of STOP ERA, and her relationship to the Mormon Church.
#107, "End of Phyllis Schlafly; anti ERA group, October 4, n.d."
Continuing footage of Phyllis Schlafly interview. She discusses the personal sacrifices she has made for the movement, her profession as a writer, the role of minority women in the anti-ERA movement, and the various negative effects she believes will result from the ERA. A group of STOP ERA women from Virginia discuss their personal views on the ERA and the state of the bill in Virginia.
#108, "Bowl-A-Thon #1, n.d."
*Sound stops working at the 5-minute mark.
A group of women bowl for a Richmond NOW ERA fundraiser in Richmond, Virginia, led by Laurabelle Yoder.
#109, "Bowl-A-Thon #2, n.d."
Continuing footage of the Richmond NOW ERA bowling fundraiser in Richmond, Virginia. The organizer of the fundraiser, Laurabelle Yoder, discusses her correspondence with Virginia Representative Satterfield regarding the ERA.
#110, "Bowl-A-Thon #3, n.d."
Continuing footage of the Richmond NOW ERA bowling fundraiser in Richmond, Virginia on August 26, "Women's Equality Day." The organizer of the fundraiser, Laurabelle Yoder, discusses her personal dedication to the pro-ERA movement, the arrest of Jean Marshall Clark, Robert's Rules of Order, and upcoming events. Laurabelle Yoder then interviews Congressman James about his predictions for the future of the ERA in Virginia.
#111, "Who Will Protect the Family? by Victoria Costello, 1981"
This is the edited, final version of "Who Will Protect the Family?" narrated by Reporter Frances Fitzgerald.
#112, "Thea Barrow interview, part 1, 1979"
Thea Barrow, a prominent lawyer, is interviewed by Marie Torre. Topics include her anti-abortion stance, her relationship to the "Right to Life" movement, the "New Right," and single-issue politics.
#113, "Thea Barrow interview, part 2, 1979"
Continuing footage of the Thea Barrow interview with Marie Torre. They reshoot various questions for the final cut.
#114, "Thea Barrow interview, 1979"
Continuing footage of the Thea Barrow interview with Marie Torre. They reshoot various questions for the final cut. Topics include the "New Right," abortion vs. child abuse, and her departure from the "Right to Life" movement.
#115, "Midge Costanza interview, n.d."
An interview with Margaret ("Midge") Costanza, President Jimmy Carter's Assistant to the President for Public Liaison. Topics include her reactions to Phyllis Schlafly's attitudes about the ERA, the issue of homosexuality and the ERA, equal pay for equal work, the effects of the ERA on the family, the ERA ratification extension, her resignation from her White House position, etc. Filming then shifts to the National NOW Action Center, where NOW activists are meeting and discussing plans with one another.
#116, "Richmond, VA, pre march, 1978"
Laurabelle Yoder, her husband Reverend Larry Yoder, and their son Marcus, are interviewed in their home in Richmond, Virginia. Topics include Laurabelle's teaching career, Larry's job within the Baptist Church, Laurabelle's Baptist minister father, liberal Baptists, stereotypes about Baptists, Baptists and ERA, religion and feminism, "women's lib," public education, their interpretations of the Bible, Virginia elections, and the motivations of anti-ERA activists.
#117, "Richmond, VA, pre march 2, 1978"
Continuing footage of the Yoder family. Topics include lobbying Representative Satterfield and why Laurabelle believes we need the ERA. Laurabelle's father and mother then join the discussion, and eventually Larry and Laurabelle's friend Chris arrives at the house. Laurabelle's father discusses his views on gender roles, his religious views, and his opinion on his daughter's political views.
#118, "Richmond, VA, evening #3, 1978"
Continuing footage of the Yoder family. Topics include the coherence of the family, their opinions on the ERA, religion, the Southern Baptist church, and female pastors, the rise of the conservative movement, Phyllis Schlafly, and the pros and cons of the ERA.
#119 "Larry Yoder Interview"
Footage of Mr. Yoder
#120, "Excerpts from ERA: A family matter; ERA for Better or Worse; Abortion; right to Live vs. Right to Choose; None of the Above, n.d."
The first half of the DVD contains miscellaneous clips of subject matter already covered in the other DVDs, such as the ERA March on Washington, Laurabelle Yoder, and clips from "ERA: A Family Matter," produced and directed by Victoria Costello (featuring the Yoder family and Laurabelle Yoder's fight for the ERA). There is also footage of Beth McAllister; anti-ERA protests in Raleigh, North Carolina; Marilyn DeVries and Alice Winn Gatsis at the WPJL radio station; and Gloria Steinem. The second half of the DVD is a PBS broadcast hosted by Marie Torre, entitled "Abortion: Right to Life vs. Right to Choose."
#121, "NOW March #12, 1978"
Footage from the NOW March on Washington, D.C. in 1978. Speeches by various women cover the ERA and women's equality, equal pay for equal work/economic equality, the role of minority women within the movement, President Jimmy Carter's support of the ERA and equal rights for women, National ERA Lobbying Day, Phyllis Schlafly, and Congress' ERA extension. Speakers include Patricia Roberts Harris, Midge Costanza, and Eleanor Smeal.
#122, "NOW March #13, 1978"
Continuing footage from the NOW March on Washington, D.C. in 1978. Gloria Steinem gives a speech in which she talks about the history of the women's and civil rights movements, suffrage, Second Wave feminism, and inequitable pay distribution.
#123, "NOW March #16, 1978"
Continuing footage from the NOW March on Washington, D.C. in 1978.
Laurabelle Yoder and her daughter are filmed in the crowd, talking to various protestors, including older ERA supporters.
FIGHTING FOR THE OBVIOUS:
#1, "Fighting for the Obvious: Peggy Madigan interview, #1, n.d."
Interview with Peggy Madigan, a volunteer organizer for the Chicago NOW chapter. She discusses the effects of the women's rights movement on her family, the departure from her financial career, what the ERA means for women who are not involved in the struggle, the resistance of the Republican Party and President Reagan to grant women their rights and their fight against the ERA, and how the women's movement might react to the potential defeat of the ERA.
#2, "Fighting for the Obvious: Peggy Madigan interview, #2," n.d.
Continuing footage of the interview with Peggy Madigan. She discusses her reasons for joining NOW, her roles and duties as a NOW volunteer organizer, her attitude towards other women working on the ERA campaign, why the ERA might fail, her experiences lobbying at the Springfield (Illinois) Capitol, and her feelings about the American political system.
#3, "Fighting for the Obvious: Peggy Madigan interview, #3," n.d.
Continuing footage of the interview with Peggy Madigan. She discusses the lessons that the ERA will teach American men and women, the participation of men within the ERA movement, the similarities between the anti-Vietnam war movement and the women's movement, and her future within the women's movement after the fight for ERA.
#4, "Fighting For the Obvious:" Carol Swinney interview, #1," n.d.
Interview with Carol Swinney, the Outreach Coordinator at NOW. She discusses her responsibilities at NOW and the ERA Countdown Office, which include informing the community about the ERA, writing editorials and letters to the editor of various publications, and mobilizing various women's groups around ERA. Swinney also mentions which women's groups she finds most helpful in the fight for ERA (Coalition of Labor Union Women, Women Employed, UAW). Other topics include the cooperation of the labor movement and the potential failure of the ERA.
#5, "Fighting For the Obvious:" Carol Swinney interview, #2," n.d.
*Carol Swinney footage ends at the 12-minute mark. The last four minutes show pictures of various ERA advocates.
Continuing footage of the interview with Carol Swinney. She discusses how she deals with tension and struggles between NOW and various other organizations, how long she's been involved in the ERA campaign and why she joined the struggle, and the concerns she has for future generations (including her daughter).
#6, "Fighting For the Obvious:" Carol Swinney interview, #3," n.d.
Continuing footage of the interview with Carol Swinney. She discusses how she overcomes discouragement, the most frustrating part of her job, her greatest accomplishment on the ERA campaign, her most memorable experiences working on the campaign, her work with Illinois Republican Lieutenant Governor candidate Susan Catania, and the implications of the ERA's potential failure.
#7, "Fighting For the Obvious:" Carol Swinney interview, #4 [#7]," n.d.
Continuing footage of the interview with Carol Swinney. She discusses the difficulty in raising children within the current political and social climate, the future of grassroots political organizing, the intersectionality of the various social movements (Civil Rights, Women's, etc.), "Solidarity Day," the future of the women's rights movement after the ERA struggle, and her personal struggles and motivations as an African-American woman.
#8, "Fighting for the Obvious: Mary Brandon interview, #1 [#8]," n.d.
Interview with Mary Brandon, a work coordinator for the Chicago NOW chapter. She discusses her decision to work for NOW, her educational qualifications, her visit to the Springfield Capitol, and her opinions on politicians.
#9, "Fighting for the Obvious: Mary Brandon interview, #2 [#9]," n.d.
*The last three minutes shows a picture of a NOW protest.
Continuing footage of the interview with Mary Brandon. She discusses her speculations as to why the ERA might fail, how women will react if the ERA does not pass, what she has learned from the ERA campaign, the future of the women's rights movement, and the anti-women policies of the Reagan administration.
#10, "Fighting for the Obvious, Linda Miller NOW meeting re: student lobby day, #11," n.d.
Interview with Linda Miller, the co-director of the ERA Countdown Campaign. She discusses her nine-year involvement with NOW, her current responsibilities at NOW, the evolution of NOW and the women's movement, the resistance of the Republican Party, her reactions to various male politicians' attitudes towards NOW activists, and NOW's strategies for passing ERA.
#11, "Fighting for the Obvious, Springfield #3, Linda Miller NOW interview, #12," n.d.
Continuing footage of the interview with Linda Miller. She discusses how her personal life has changed as a result of her involvement with NOW, the reactions of various legislators to NOW's ERA policies, her motivations for working so hard on the campaign, and her predictions for the future of the women's movement after the ERA.
#12, "Fighting for the Obvious, Springfield #4,Linda Miller interview, #13, n.d."
Continuing footage of the interview with Linda Miller. She discusses the lessons that the women's movement has learned from the ERA campaign, why she believes there is so much resistance to the ERA, and how she became involved with the women's movement.
#13, "Fighting for the Obvious: Kathy Railsback interview, #14, n.d."
Interview with Kelly Railsback, a member of the Springfield NOW chapter. She discusses NOW's battle with Illinois Republic Senator Forrest Etheridge.
#14, "Fighting for the Obvious: Kathy Railsback interview, #15, n.d."
Continuing footage of the interview with Kathy Railsback. She discusses the Illinois 3/5-rule change legislation, and a detailed account of her meeting with Illinois Republican Senator Forrest Etheridge on his potential vote against the ERA.
#15, "Fighting for the Obvious: Wilma Scott Heide interview, #16, n.d."
Interview with Wilma Scott Heide. She discusses how she came to be a feminist; how she disrupted the Senate Subcommittee on Constitutional Amendments on February 17, 1970; the most important things that the feminist movement has learned from the ERA struggle; and the biggest achievements of the feminist movement in the last fifteen years.
#16, Fighting for the Obvious: Wilma Scott Heide interview, #17, n.d."
Continuing footage of the interview with Wilma Scott Heide. She discusses the history of civil disobedience within the women's movement and the ERA struggle, her opinions on the American political system, and how the women's movement has changed since the mid-1960s.
#17, Fighting for the Obvious: Wilma Scott Heide interview, #18, n.d."
Continuing footage of the interview with Wilma Scott Heide. She discusses why the ERA might fail, why she believes the ERA won't fail, the problems with the mass media and how it has failed the women's movement, how to rally if the ERA fails, how she stays motivated and why all women should stay motivated.
#18, Fighting for the Obvious: Wilma Scott Heide interview, #19, n.d."
Continuing footage of the interview with Wilma Scott Heide. She discusses feminism's definitions of male and female, what would happen if the values of feminism were applied to public policy, and how feminism affirms men and women as whole.
#19, "Fighting for the Obvious: Wilma Scott Heide interview, #20, n.d."
Continuing silent footage of Wilma Scott Heide, showing her walking, talking to the interviewer, etc.
#20, "Fighting for the Obvious: Interview with Rep. Donald Deuster (anti-ERA), #21, n.d."